<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>JMFT - Python</title><link href="https://jmft.dev/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://jmft.dev/feeds/python.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://jmft.dev/</id><updated>2024-07-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Logging in Python</title><link href="https://jmft.dev/logging-in-python.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2024-07-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-07-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>J. M. F. Tsang</name></author><id>tag:jmft.dev,2024-07-07:/logging-in-python.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having reliable, detailed but searchable logs is an essential part of
any application, especially of long-running services that need to be
debugged and monitored for uptime and stability. As one of the oldest
modules in the Python standard library, the &lt;code&gt;logging&lt;/code&gt; module provides a
very powerful set of tools for …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having reliable, detailed but searchable logs is an essential part of
any application, especially of long-running services that need to be
debugged and monitored for uptime and stability. As one of the oldest
modules in the Python standard library, the &lt;code&gt;logging&lt;/code&gt; module provides a
very powerful set of tools for logging, but its design and behaviour
also shows its age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the basics are covered in the &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/howto/logging.html"&gt;official
tutorial&lt;/a&gt; and full details
are given in the &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/logging.html"&gt;reference
docs&lt;/a&gt;, this article
collects together the most commonly seen concepts from different parts
of the docs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why use &lt;code&gt;logging&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although it takes some setup (which will be covered below), It is
strongly preferable to use the features of &lt;code&gt;logging&lt;/code&gt;, rather than
&lt;code&gt;print()&lt;/code&gt;, for diagnostics and debugging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Diagnostic messages vs. machine-readable output&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;logging&lt;/code&gt; module allows one to define different handlers for
different types of messages. Besides (or instead of) printing the
message to &lt;code&gt;stdout,&lt;/code&gt; it may be helpful to print messages to &lt;code&gt;stderr&lt;/code&gt;, or
to do something else with them like submitting them to a database.
Urgent, critical messages may need to be emailed or sent as push
notifications.  Diagnostic, human-readable messages (which aren't
necessarily &lt;em&gt;error&lt;/em&gt; messages) should generally be separated from
machine-readable output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Thread-safety&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loggers are thread-safe. Concurrent threads logging to the same file do
not interfere with each other; whenever a thread attempts to write to a
log file, that thread has exclusive ownership of that file while it is
writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By contrast, the &lt;code&gt;print()&lt;/code&gt; function or writing to a stream with
&lt;code&gt;f.write()&lt;/code&gt; are not thread safe, so that messages from two threads may
interfere with each other. For example, it is not guaranteed that each
message is printed on its own line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;message frommessage from thread 2
 thread 1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Loggers, handlers, filters and formatters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logging functionality is provided by four main classes. From &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/logging.html#logger-objects"&gt;the
docs&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/logging.html#logger-objects"&gt;Loggers&lt;/a&gt;
expose the interface that application code directly uses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/logging.html#handler-objects"&gt;Handlers&lt;/a&gt;
send the &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/logging.html#logrecord-objects"&gt;log records&lt;/a&gt;
(created by loggers) to the appropriate destination.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/logging.html#filter-objects"&gt;Filters&lt;/a&gt;
provide a finer grained facility for determining which log records to
output.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/logging.html#formatter-objects"&gt;Formatters&lt;/a&gt; specify the layout of log records in the final output.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The logic and the relationship between these classes is summarised in
the flowchart from the
&lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/howto/logging.html#logging-flow"&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt;:
![[content/images/python-logging-flowchart.png]]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a basic setup it is only necessary to configure a logger; but
configuring handlers and formatters can make your logs more informative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code&gt;Logger&lt;/code&gt; objects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do not instantiate &lt;code&gt;Logger&lt;/code&gt; directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;# Not like this!
logger = logging.Logger(...)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, create them using the factory function &lt;code&gt;logging.getLogger()&lt;/code&gt;, providing a name for the logger:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;# Like this
logger = logging.getLogger(&amp;quot;example_app&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing so allows the &lt;code&gt;logging&lt;/code&gt; module to keep track of all the loggers
that are in use, as well as to return the same instance if the same name
is used across different modules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Configuring the logger&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One the logger instance has been created, you can add handlers to it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;import logging

logger = logging.getLogger(&amp;quot;example_app&amp;quot;)
logger.setLevel(logging.INFO)
handler = logging.FileHandler(&amp;quot;example_app.log&amp;quot;)
logger.addHandler(handler)

# usage
logger.info(&amp;quot;hello&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The root logger and why not to use it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If no logger is configured, or if you use one of the module-level
functions such as  &lt;code&gt;logging.info()&lt;/code&gt; as opposed to &lt;code&gt;logger.info()&lt;/code&gt;, then
the default behaviour is to use the &amp;quot;root logger&amp;quot;. This is a &lt;code&gt;Logger&lt;/code&gt;
that is available globally. You can also obtain it with
&lt;code&gt;logging.getLogger()&lt;/code&gt;, providing no argument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Although the root logger can be used without any setup, it is usually
a good idea to configure your own loggers.&lt;/strong&gt; By using different loggers,
the logging output of different components of a program can be
configured independently of each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if you are developing a library, let's say &lt;code&gt;libfoo&lt;/code&gt;, that
is intended for use in other applications, you can create your own
logger:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;# libfoo.py
import logging
logger = logging.getLogger(&amp;quot;libfoo&amp;quot;)
# then configure your logger
# and then
logger.info(&amp;quot;logfoo is doing stuff&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then a client of your code can both set up their own logging and
modify your code's behaviour:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;# client.py
import logging
import libfoo

logger = logging.getLogger(&amp;quot;client&amp;quot;)
libfoo.logger.setLevel(logging.WARNING)  # suppress INFO messages
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code&gt;Handler&lt;/code&gt; objects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many subclasses of &lt;code&gt;Handler&lt;/code&gt;, providing different options for what to do with log messages. The two most common are &lt;code&gt;StreamHandler(stream)&lt;/code&gt;, which writes to a stream such as &lt;code&gt;sys.stderr&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;FileHandler(filename)&lt;/code&gt;, which appends messages to a file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other &lt;code&gt;Handler&lt;/code&gt; classes are provided in the &lt;code&gt;logging.handlers&lt;/code&gt; module (&lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/logging.handlers.html"&gt;doc&lt;/a&gt;), and some useful ones include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;RotatingFileHandler&lt;/code&gt; , which writes to successive files (&lt;code&gt;app.log.1&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;app.log.2&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;em&gt;etc.&lt;/em&gt;) keeping each file below a maximum size;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;SocketHandler&lt;/code&gt;, which emits messages as TCP packets;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;HTTPHandler&lt;/code&gt;, which emits messages as &lt;code&gt;GET&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;POST&lt;/code&gt; requests to a webserver; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;SMTPHandler&lt;/code&gt;, which sends email.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose the handlers that are suitable for your architecture. Since each handler can be configured separately, one might for example configure a &lt;code&gt;SMTPHandler&lt;/code&gt; to only report important messages such as &lt;code&gt;ERROR&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;EXCEPTION&lt;/code&gt;, while &lt;code&gt;StreamHandler&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;FileHandler&lt;/code&gt; to contain &lt;code&gt;DEBUG&lt;/code&gt; messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Formatters and Filters&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formatters and filters give further control over how messages are processed. Filters are associated with both loggers and handlers and can be configured differently for different handlers, so that different handlers may choose to emit different messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A handler may have a formatter; if no formatter is defined then the default behaviour is print just the message by itself. However, formatters can be configured to show various pieces of metadata about each log message (&lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/logging.html#logrecord-attributes"&gt;doc&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a good idea to include timestamps as well as information about what emitted the message. This is done by passing arguments to &lt;code&gt;Formatter&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;import logging

logger = logging.getLogger(&amp;quot;example&amp;quot;)
logger.setLevel(logging.INFO)
handler = logging.StreamHandler()
logger.addHandler(handler)
formatter = logging.Formatter(
  &amp;quot;%(asctime)s %(levelname)s %(filename)s:%(lineno)s %(message)s&amp;quot;,
  datefmt=&amp;quot;%Y-%m-%d %H:%M:%S&amp;quot;
)
handler.setFormatter(formatter)

logger.info(&amp;quot;Hello, world&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;prints:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;2024-07-14 17:21:20,988 INFO foo.py:12 Hello, world
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Logging levels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are five predefined logging levels: &lt;code&gt;DEBUG&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;INFO&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;WARNING&lt;/code&gt;,
&lt;code&gt;ERROR&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;CRITICAL&lt;/code&gt; . These are to be used for messages of increasing
seriousness. Each logger or filter must be set to a level, and ignores
messages that are lower than that level. The default logging level is
&lt;code&gt;WARNING&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some good practices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above: Use &lt;code&gt;logging&lt;/code&gt; where possible instead of &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt;,
so that diagnostic messages are separated from output that needs to be
machine-readable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't use the root logger, always configure a custom logger. This
makes it possible to configure separate logging behaviour between
different modules or libraries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a minimum, log messages should contain a timestamp. Otherwise, in a
log file it will not be possible to discern whether a log message was
triggered by a recent event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also a good idea to include a reference to whatever caused the
log message to be emitted. Including the filename, line number and
name of the function in the formatter is a good first start.
However, this may not be fully informative if the log message is
inside a function that is called from many sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logging the arguments passed to the function can also be helpful.
But this must be done with care, if the arguments passed are complex
objects with many fields, or if they contain sensitive information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like to invent &amp;quot;sentinel&amp;quot; words (my term, I can't remember if there
is an official term for this) that are specific to the particular
feature being logged about. By using a word that won't be used
anywhere else, it makes it easier to search for that word in the logs
using &lt;code&gt;grep&lt;/code&gt;. For example, I used the French word &amp;quot;telecharger&amp;quot;
instead of &amp;quot;download&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;funcy&lt;/code&gt; library provides a number of function decorators or
context managers that help with logging calls to and returns from
functions, which are particularly valuable when profiling code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;stderr or stdout?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The default behaviour of &lt;code&gt;StreamHandler&lt;/code&gt; is to write log messages to
&lt;code&gt;stderr&lt;/code&gt; rather than &lt;code&gt;stdout&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When writing shell utilities, writing diagnostic messages to &lt;code&gt;stderr&lt;/code&gt;
instead of &lt;code&gt;stdout&lt;/code&gt; is useful if the program needs to produce
machine-readable output, for example, to pipe into another process.
Separating diagnostic messages into a separate stream will allow those
messages to be more meaningful, detailed and human-readable, while
keeping the output in a standard format. This also avoids accidentally
piping such messages into the other program, which can have unexpected
(or even dangerous) results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, for long-running services such as web apps, &lt;a href="https://12factor.net/logs"&gt;The
Twelve-Factor App&lt;/a&gt; recommends writing all
messages to &lt;code&gt;stdout&lt;/code&gt;, using a single stream. This stream can then be
directed either to a regular file or to an external service which can
then provide further services, such as searching, trend analysis or
forwarding high-level messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The appropriate choice therefore depends on what the program output is
used for. In either case, using the &lt;code&gt;logging&lt;/code&gt; module and the
&lt;code&gt;StreamHandler&lt;/code&gt; class provides an abstraction that sidesteps this
question for the code that actually emits the log message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Copy-and-paste example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;# logger.py
import logging

def configure_logger() -&amp;gt; logging.Logger:
    &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;This stuff goes into its own function in order not to pollute the
    module-level namespace; but since this is in its own module that
    doesn't matter too much.
    &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
    logger = logging.getLogger(&amp;quot;my_app&amp;quot;)
    handler = logging.StreamHandler()
    logger.addHandler(handler)
    formatter = logging.Formatter(
      &amp;quot;%(asctime)s %(levelname)s %(filename)s:%(lineno)s %(message)s&amp;quot;,
      datefmt=&amp;quot;%Y-%m-%d %H:%M:%S&amp;quot;
    )
    handler.setFormatter(formatter)

    return logger

# This gets initialized only once, even if this module is imported
# multiple times.
logger: logging.Logger = configure_logger()

# Allow logger to be imported from other modules
__all__ = [&amp;quot;logger&amp;quot;]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, in another module in the same package:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;# code.py
from .logger import logger

logger.info(&amp;quot;Hello&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</content><category term="Python"/><category term="python"/><category term="backend"/></entry><entry><title>Object creation patterns in Python: Static factory methods</title><link href="https://jmft.dev/static-factory-methods-in-python.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2024-05-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>J. M. F. Tsang</name></author><id>tag:jmft.dev,2024-05-21:/static-factory-methods-in-python.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The basic way to create and initialize an object in Python is using the
default constructor, defined as the &lt;code&gt;__init__()&lt;/code&gt; method:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;class MyClass:
    def __init__(self, x: float) -&amp;gt; None:
        self.x: float = x
        print(f&amp;quot;created an object with x = {x}&amp;quot;)


obj = MyClass(5)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually, initial values of instance variables …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The basic way to create and initialize an object in Python is using the
default constructor, defined as the &lt;code&gt;__init__()&lt;/code&gt; method:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;class MyClass:
    def __init__(self, x: float) -&amp;gt; None:
        self.x: float = x
        print(f&amp;quot;created an object with x = {x}&amp;quot;)


obj = MyClass(5)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually, initial values of instance variables are specified using
arguments to &lt;code&gt;__init__()&lt;/code&gt;, and assigned to the variables. The body of
&lt;code&gt;__init__()&lt;/code&gt; may also contain other steps, such as precomputing other
other variables based on these instance attributes, or, as in this
example, logging the creation of an object. &lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Resource allocation
such as opening files should generally &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be done in an initializer,
but in a &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/reference/datamodel.html#context-managers"&gt;context
manager&lt;/a&gt;,
so that client code doesn't have to take care of deallocation.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dataclasses and kwargs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a class has many instance variables, it is common to &lt;strong&gt;use keyword
arguments when initializing them&lt;/strong&gt;, which makes the meaning of each
argument more explicit and allows arguments to be reordered later.
Furthermore, such classes are often good candidates for making into
&lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/dataclasses.html"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dataclasses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
since the &lt;code&gt;@dataclass&lt;/code&gt; decorator automatically creates an &lt;code&gt;__init__()&lt;/code&gt;
method with the necessary arguments and that assigns them to the
instance variables:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;@dataclass
class Person:
    # types are not enforced at runtime, but are checked by type
    # checkers
    name: str
    age: int

    # More complex types, including recursive types, are allowed. Use
    # `field`
    occupation: Optional[str] = field(default=None)
    best_friend: &amp;quot;Person&amp;quot; = field(default=None)

    # an __init___ method is automatically generated, but you can still
    # create a __post_init__ method for additional behaviour like
    # logging

    def __post_init__(self):
        print(f&amp;quot;Created new Person: {self}&amp;quot;)


# Use kwargs when creating instances
p = Person(name=&amp;quot;Sir Robin&amp;quot;, age=32, occupation=&amp;quot;knight&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as automatically providing the &lt;code&gt;__init__()&lt;/code&gt; method, dataclasses
also automatically provide methods such as &lt;code&gt;__repr__()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;__eq__()&lt;/code&gt;,
further reducing the amount of boilerplate code and allowing you to use
a more declarative style of programming that focuses on the structure of
the class (and makes it easier to add or remove fields witout needing to
worry about updating all these methods).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While using dataclasses makes it easy to create an initializer even for
objects with many fields, there are nonetheless some limitations of
creating objects using the basic syntax &lt;code&gt;Person(...)&lt;/code&gt;. To provide more
expressive ways to create objects, various &lt;em&gt;object creation patterns&lt;/em&gt;
have been developed over the years, and are now standard fare in large
projects, including the standard library itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of this post will discuss the &lt;strong&gt;static factory methods
pattern&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows you to provide multiple, distinct ways to
instantiate a class without having a complicated &lt;code&gt;__init__()&lt;/code&gt; method. In
a future post I shall discuss the &lt;strong&gt;builder pattern&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets you
gradually build up a complex object by passing around the information
needed to create it rather than requiring all the information in one go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The static factory method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goal:&lt;/strong&gt; Provide multiple, distinct ways of instantiating a class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Explicit is better than implicit.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;small&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen_of_Python"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Zen of Python&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cases you want to provide multiple ways to obtain instances of a
class. To do that, you can provide &lt;em&gt;static factory methods&lt;/em&gt; in your
class: these are class methods that create and return instances.
&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;(The name comes from Java, which does not distinguish between
class methods and static methods.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A classic example is a &lt;code&gt;Point2D&lt;/code&gt; class that represents a point in the
plane. It is desired to be able to create instances of &lt;code&gt;Point2D&lt;/code&gt; by
specifying either the point's Cartesian coordinates or its polar
coordinates. To achieve this, we define static factory methods
&lt;code&gt;from_cartesians()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;from_polars()&lt;/code&gt; that return instances of
&lt;code&gt;Point2D&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;import math


@dataclass
class Point2D:
    x: float
    y: float

    # __init__(self, x, y) is automatically generated

    @classmethod
    def from_cartesians(cls, x: float, y: float) -&amp;gt; &amp;quot;Point2D&amp;quot;:
        return cls(x=x, y=y)

    @classmethod
    def from_polars(cls, r: float, theta: float) -&amp;gt; &amp;quot;Point2D&amp;quot;:
        if r &amp;lt; 0:
            raise ValueError(&amp;quot;Radial coordinate must be nonnegative&amp;quot;)
        return cls(x=r * math.cos(theta), y=r * math.sin(theta))

    
p: Point2D = Point2D.from_polars(r=4, theta=0.5 * math.pi)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the &lt;code&gt;__init__()&lt;/code&gt; method (automatically created by &lt;code&gt;@dataclass&lt;/code&gt;)
already gives us a way of instantiating a &lt;code&gt;Point2D&lt;/code&gt; through its
Cartesian coordinates, we nonetheless provide a &lt;code&gt;from_cartesians()&lt;/code&gt;
method. There are two major benefits to using this method oer the basic
initializer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is more explicit about what the input numbers mean.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it is desired to store the polar coordinates, rather than the
Cartesian coordinates, as fields, the class methods can be updated
without affecting client code; whereas instantiations with &lt;code&gt;Point2D(...)&lt;/code&gt;
would need to be updated. (This is referred to as &amp;quot;invariance under
refactoring&amp;quot; and allows developers to work on different parts of a
codebase without hugely affecting each other.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For contrast, this is what the class might look like if we wanted to
allow the user to specify either Cartesian or polar coordinates when
creating a &lt;code&gt;Point2D&lt;/code&gt;, all in the &lt;code&gt;__init__()&lt;/code&gt; method:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;@dataclass(init=False)  # we provide our own __init__() method
class Point2D:
    x: float
    y: float

    def __init__(
        self, 
        x: Optional[float] = None, 
        y: Optional[float] = None, 
        r: Optional[float] = None, 
        theta: Optional[float] = None
    ):
        using_cartesians = x is not None and y is not None
        using_polars = r is not None and theta is not None
        if using_cartesians and not using_polars:
            self.x, self.y = x, y
            return
        if using_polars and not using_cartesians:
            if r &amp;lt; 0:
              raise ValueError(&amp;quot;Radial coordinate must be nonnegative&amp;quot;)
            self.x = r * math.cos(theta)
            self.y = r * math.sin(theta)
            return
        
        raise ValueError(&amp;quot;Either specify x and y or specify r and theta, but not both.&amp;quot;)


p: Point2D = Point2D(r=4, theta=0.5 * math.pi)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is clearly more complex and less expressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Static factory methods are a common pattern in object oriented
languages. Python doesn't have method overloading (unlike C/++ and
Java) and so it is not possible to define multiple &lt;code&gt;__init__()&lt;/code&gt; methods
with different signatures. But even in languages like Java it is often
recommended to use static factory methods instead of overloaded
constructors, for the expressiveness. &lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Indeed, this is the
very first item in Joshua Bloch's &lt;a href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/effective-java-3rd/9780134686097/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Effective Java&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abstract base classes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real power of static factory methods comes when working with
abstract classes. While (by definition) you cannot directly instantiate
an abstract class, you can emulate such an instantiation providing a
static factory method on the abstract base class that chooses an
appropriate subclass and produces an instance of that class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A typical use case is to provide the user with a simplified interface
while internally having several underlying implementations. Consider the
following interface, which declares a single method for calculating the
integral of a function between two points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;import abc


class Integrator(abc.ABC):
    @abc.abstractmethod
    def integrate(self, f: Callable[[float], float], a: float, b: float) -&amp;gt; float:
        &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;Calculate the integral of the function f between a and b.&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot; 
        raise NotImplementedError
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The subclasses implement different methods of integration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;class EulerIntegrator(Integrator):
    def __init__(self, n: int = 10):
        self.n = n
        
    def integrate(self, f, a, b):
        # Even for such an inaccurate scheme, this is a terrible 
        # implementation! It is horrendously inefficient and doesn't
        # properly handle floating point errors. This is just for
        # illustration purposes.
        dx = (b - a) / self.n
        x = a
        s = 0
        while x &amp;lt; b:
            s += f(x) * dx
            x += dx
        return s
    
class AdamsBashforthIntegrator(Integrator): ...  # similarly
class TrapeziumIntegrator(Integrator): ...  # similarly
class RK4Integrator(Integrator): ...  # similarly
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The appropriate choice of integration method depends on the function.
For example, the Adams–Bashorth integrator has a lower order of
accuracy than RK4, but performs better against stiff equations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the client may wish to choose an integrator for themself, as the
developer of the &lt;code&gt;Integrator&lt;/code&gt; class one may wish to provide the user a
shortcut for common cases without requiring them to know the details of
the particular implementation. To achieve this, the &lt;code&gt;Integrator&lt;/code&gt; class
could provide a static factory method that returns an appropriate
instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;class Integrator(abc.ABC):
    @classmethod
    def create(cls, stiff: bool = False) -&amp;gt; &amp;quot;Integrator&amp;quot;:
        if stiff:
            return AdamsBashforthIntegrator(...)  # with suitable params
        else:
              return RK4Integrator(...)  # ditto
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;with example usage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;integrator = Integrator.create(stiff=True)
print(integrator.integrate(lambda x: x ** 2, 1, 2))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other numerical operations that can be calculated using different
algorithms are similarly candidates for such a structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Caveat and conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The examples above are smallish classes that nonetheless benefit from
having multiple ways to create them. With that said, a class that has
very different behaviours depending on how it is initialized may be too
complicated, and be a candidate for refactoring into smaller classes
each with fewer responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, the static factory method pattern is commonly used
not only in Python but also in other languages. The benefits are the
same: using static factory methods (a) allows the user to more
explicitly state how an object should be produced from input data
(&lt;code&gt;Point2D.from_cartesians(3, 4)&lt;/code&gt; versus &lt;code&gt;Point2D(3, 4)&lt;/code&gt;), and (b) allows
the class to rework what data it stores internally or which
implementation of an abstract class to provide.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Python"/><category term="python"/><category term="object-oriented-programming"/><category term="design-patterns"/></entry><entry><title>for loops in Python are a bit weird</title><link href="https://jmft.dev/for-loops-in-python-are-a-bit-weird.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2024-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>J. M. F. Tsang</name></author><id>tag:jmft.dev,2024-02-11:/for-loops-in-python-are-a-bit-weird.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A quiz:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does the following JavaScript code print and why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-javascript"&gt;for (let i = 0; i &amp;lt; 3; i++) {
  console.log(i);
  i -= 3
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does the following Python code print and why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;for i in range(3):
    print(i)
    i -= 3

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</content><category term="Python"/><category term="python"/><category term="javascript"/></entry></feed>